（椿）《ちょっと　公生！》→
Come on, Kousei!
《膝　擦りむいたくらいで
泣くな！》→
Who cries over a skinned knee?
《あんた　男でしょ！
あたしなんか→
And you call yourself a man!
Just look at me! My ankle was all like "snap"!
足が　ぐきってなったんだぞ！
ぐきって！　うっ　うわ…》
（公生）《椿が土手で
大車輪なんて　させるから！》
It's your fault for making me do the...
Oh, shut up!
（椿）《うるさい！　ハァ…》
《でも　公生のケガ
脚で　よかった》
But thank goodness it was only your leg.
《もし　手にケガさせてたら→
If you'd hurt your hands,
公生ママに
殺されちゃうところだった》
your mom woulda killed me.
Stop crying, you dummy!
《泣くな！　バカ公生！
あたしまで…》
You're making me cry...
Here's a towel and a change of clothes.
（公生）あっ　はい。
タオルと着替え。→
制服　乾燥機に　かけとくから！
I'll put your uniform in the dryer.
（かをり）ありがとう。
家の人は？
Thanks.
Where's your family?
（公生）父さんは　仕事で
家を空けることが多いんだ。
My dad's usually away on business.
（かをり）へえ～
思ったより大きいな。
Hey, it's bigger than I thought.
（公生）こんな所にいた。
コーヒーでいい？
There you are.
Is coffee okay? I can get you some warm milk, too...
温かい牛乳も…。
うおりゃー！
Wh-What the hell?!
ななな…　何を！？
ごめんね　ごめんね…。
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry...
健全な演奏は　健全な環境から！
まずは掃除だ！　換気ー！
Wholesome playing starts with a wholesome environment!
Our first order of business is cleanup! Air this place out!
お隣だ。　椿ちゃーん。
違うぞ！　これには訳が…！
Hey, Tsubaki! You're right next door!
It's not what it looks like! I can explain!
Kao?
（椿）《かをちゃん？
公生の服？》→
In Kousei's clothes?
《ぬれた髪？》
ひいー！！
With wet hair?
What?!
（椿）ぬおー！
うおりゃー！
（椿）おら　おら　おら…！
（部員）気合　入ってるな　椿のやつ。
Tsubaki sure is fired up.
（部員）荒れてるだけじゃない？
Looks like straight-up violence to me.
Countdown to Regionals
Days  Left
（柏木）空元気でも
ないより　ましね。
I guess that's better than nothing.
≪[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]（♪♪『エチュード
ホ短調　作品２５－５』）
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]（♪♪『エチュード　ホ短調　作品２５－５』）
これ　僕？
That's... me?
そう！　たった今　君が弾いた
ピアノの録音。
Yup!
I recorded what you just played on tape.
選択課題曲　ショパン　エチュード
作品　２５－５。
Your set piece is Chopin's Étude Op. 25 No. 5.
嘘だー！　テンポも音もバラバラ！
No way!
The tempo and pitch are so out of sync!
こんなの　僕じゃなーい！
That can't be me!
Man, he sucks.
下手くそね。
（渡）下手くそ。
Got that right.
I can't compete like this!
《こんなんで　コンクール！？》
I'm backing out. Yeah. If I act now, I can still...
《やめよう。
そうだ　今なら　まだ…》
I already signed you up!
もう　書類　出しといた。
僕の財布！
Is that my wallet?!
で　どんなもんなの？
その大会？
So what kind of competition is this?
毎報　音楽コンクール。
The Maihou Music Competition.
名だたる演奏家を輩出した
全国規模のコンクール。
They compete at the national level, and they've produced a lot of renowned musicians.
その全国大会で優勝すれば
海外進出のチャンスも！
If you win Nationals, you could even get the chance to perform overseas!
へえー。
（渡）すげえ。
Really?
Awesome.
（椿）《かをちゃんたちの話は→
It feels like Kao's talking about
stuff from a whole different world.
私たちとは遠い
別世界の話に聞こえる》
誰か　先生に師事しなきゃ。
I've gotta find an instructor to help me prepare.
覚悟を決めろ！　これは挑戦よ。
Face it.
This is a challenge!
音が聞こえなくても
弾けるってことを→
You're gonna prove that you can play even if you can't hear your notes!
証明するのだ！
（渡・柏木）おおー。
海図にない海を帆走するには
勇気がいるのよ！
"It takes courage to sail in uncharted waters"!
誰の言葉？
スヌーピー。
Who said that?
Snoopy.
犬？
ワン！
The dog?
Woof!
What's important is how you visualize it.
大切なのは　イメージ。
（３人）うん　うん。
「あなたの指が　鍵に触れる前に
その曲を　どう弾くか→
"Before your fingers touch the keys, you must begin the piece mentally—
心の中で
考えておかなければならない」
that is, you must have it settled in your mind."
アントン・ルービンシュタイン。
Anton Rubinstein.
君は何のために　ピアノを弾くの？
Why do you play the piano?
自分のため？　誰かのため？
Is it for someone else? For yourself?
君は　この曲を　どう弾きたい？
How do you want to play this piece?
本当の君は
ショパンを　どう弾きたい？
How do you really want to play Chopin?
All right, then. Good luck!
そういうことで　よろしく。
後は　２人で頑張って！　とうっ！
I'll leave the rest to you two!
Man, you reek of sweat!
ハハハ　汗臭い！
（渡）俺　頑張る！
I'm totally pumped now!
（柏木）休憩　終わっちゃう。
（椿）死ね！
Our break's gonna be over soon.
Die!
《そうか…》
Well, then.
《また　お前と　二人ぼっちか》
Just you and me again, huh?
Chopin...
（椿の母）ショパン…。
このピアノ　コーちゃん？
Is that Kou on the piano?
（椿）うん。
（椿の母）そう　弾きはじめたのね。
So he started playing again?
（椿の母）差し入れでも
持っていこうかしら。
Maybe I should bring him something to eat.
Early Luck
Trial
Judgment
Very Unlucky
イメージは？
What's your mental image?
ヨーロッパの石畳を馬車が…。
ありきたり！　イメージ貧困！
A horse-drawn carriage rolling over cobblestones in Europe...
Unoriginal and unimaginative!
Trial
Judgment
Very Unlucky
Lucky
イメージ。
朝食に目玉焼きを…。
Image?
Sunny-side up eggs for breakfast...
庶民的！　ノーロマンチック！
Mundane and unromantic!
Judgment
Very Unlucky
Lucky
Unlucky
イメージ。
Image!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]（♪♪『エチュード　ホ短調　作品２５－５』）
Image.
《イメージ　イメージ　イメージ》
Image!
《イメージって　何だ？》
What is an image, anyway?
《曲の解釈とは　違うのか？》
What separates it from other ways you interpret music?
《君は　この曲を
どう弾きたい？》
How do you want to play this piece?
《僕は　この曲を
どう弾きたい？》
How do I want...
to play this piece?
天使みたいだ。
おとなしくしてれば。
She looks like an angel.
When she's quiet, anyway.
地区総体はどう？
（椿）準備　ばっちし。→
How are Regionals going?
We've never been more prepared.
怖いのは　ケガだけかな。
そっちは？
There's just always the risk of injury.
How about you guys?
Arima was basically tearing his hair out the other day.
この前　有馬君
頭から　煙　出てた。
もうちょっとで
見えてくると思うんだけど。
But I think he's close to showing some progress.
（椿）根　詰め過ぎじゃないかな。
廊下で　フラフラしてたし　公生。
Don't you think he's pushing himself too hard?
I mean, he was kinda reeling in the hallway.
ピアノは弾いてほしい。
I do want him to play piano, but I don't want him to suffer.
でも　苦しんでほしくない。
今　有馬君は→
Arima's trying to turn his suffering into music right now.
その苦しみを
音にしようとしている。
痛みも　苦しみも→
Exposing your pain and suffering
and revealing who you really are...
あがいた自分さえも
さらけ出して→
音に自分が宿る。
That's how we find ourselves within our music.
そうやって
私たちは　生きた音を奏でる。
It's how we make music come alive.
有馬君は　その最中。　きっと…。
That's what Arima's going through now. I'm sure of it.
《「私たち」》
"We"...
かをちゃんは　どうして
そんなに　公生に肩入れするの？
Why are you so supportive of Kousei, Kao?
うーん　何ていうか　やっぱり…。
I guess I'd have to say...
ダメダメな弟って感じかな？
He's like a hopeless kid brother, maybe?
公生は
駄目なんかじゃないよ…。
Kousei...
isn't hopeless at all...
じゃあ。
Bye!
うん　また　あした。
Yeah, see you tomorrow.
（斉藤）よっ　よう。
今　部活帰りでさ。
H-Hey.
I'm heading home from practice right now.
何してっかなっと思って。
Just wondering what you were up to.
私も　今　帰るところです。
I'm on my way home too.
最近　帰る時間　かぶりますね
私たち。　あっ…。
We're always taking off at the same time these days, huh?
[TEL]（斉藤）椿？
Tsubaki?
I'm not a part of that "we"...
（椿）私たちに　私はいない…。
[TEL]えっ？　何？
Huh? What's that?
先輩…。
[TEL]うん？
Saitou.
Yeah?
（椿）私たち　付き合いましょうか？
Do you still want to go out sometime?
Music Preparation Room
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]（♪♪『エチュード　ホ短調　作品２５－５』）
《僕は　この曲を
どう弾きたいのだろう？》
How do I want to play this piece?
《何のために…》
お疲れ。
And why?
Nice work.
《誰のために　弾きたいのだろう》
Who do I want to play it for?
今日は　もう　やめたら？
外　真っ暗。　月が奇麗だよ。
Why don't you pack it in for today?
It's totally dark outside.
And the moon's so pretty.
もうちょっと…。
Just a little longer.
私を恨んでる？
えっ？
Do you resent me?
椿ちゃんが　言ってた。
Tsubaki told me this is making you suffer.
公生は苦しんでるって。
私も知ってた。
But I already knew.
君の部屋を見て　分かってた。
I realized it when I saw your room.
音が聞こえなくなって
ピアノを捨てようとする君。
Unable to hear your music,
you try to abandon the piano...
ピアノを　よりどころとする君。
despite still clinging to it for support.
だから　目を背けるように→
That's why you try to hide it under dust and books like you're turning your back on it.
ほこりや　本で
覆い隠そうとしている。
いとしいけれど　近づけない。
You love it, but you can't go near it.
恋しいけれど　触れられない。
You miss it, but you can't touch it.
悲しいのに　痛いのに。
You're hurting and you're grieving,
私は　それに気付かないふり。
but I just turn a blind eye.
「ピアノを弾いて」
「頑張って」なんて→
Telling you to "play the piano" and "work hard" and other thoughtless things like that.
無責任なことばかり。
私のせいで　苦しんでる…。
You're suffering because of me.
ごめんね　ごめんね…。
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry...
You're the one who swept the dust away.
そのほこりを
取り払ってくれたのは　君だよ。
苦しそうか　困ったな。
So I look like I'm suffering, huh? That's not good.
苦しいのは
当たり前なんだけどな。
But of course I'd be suffering.
僕は
海図のない航路を行くんだろ？
I mean, I'm sailing in uncharted waters, right?
挑戦するのも
生み出すのも苦しいよ。
Taking on a challenge and creating something is painful.
でも　充実してる。
だから　ありがとう。
But it's fulfilling.
If anything, I should thank you.
《もう　ずっと前から
僕の世界は変わっていた》
My world already changed a while ago.
《ただ　気付かなかっただけ》
I just didn't realize it.
僕の体に積もったほこりを
払ってくれて　ありがとう。
You swept away the dust that was surrounding me.
Thank you.
《僕と出会ってくれて…》
I'm glad you found me.
《あの日から　僕の世界は
鍵盤でさえ→
Ever since that day, my whole world—keyboard and all—
カラフルになっていたんだ》
became colorful.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]（♪♪『エチュード　ホ短調　作品２５－５』）
下手くそ。
You suck.
《友達を好きな女の子》
Me and my best friend's crush.
《銀色の月から隠れるように→
The two of us in this music room in the middle of the night, as though hiding from the silver moon.
音楽室に２人　夜の中に
僕ら２人しか　いないみたいだ》
The two of us in this music room in the middle of the night, as though hiding from the silver moon.
Your Lie in April
Like there's no one else in the world.
It's time to kick off our rally for Regionals.
[ﾏｲｸ]（生徒）ただ今より
地区総体　壮行会を始めます。
Now, then. Let's hear how pumped up...
それでは　最初にサッカー部の…。
（渡）フッ
この時代に生まれた　お前らは→
What lucky boys and girls you are to have been born in this era.
とんだラッキーボーイだぜ。
渡　亮太っていうスターの誕生に
立ち会えるのだから！
All in attendance shall bear witness as a star named Watari Ryouta is born.
（女子生徒たち）キャー！
（渡）俺　カッコイイ！→
Yeah, I'm cool!
ハハハハ！　お前らに
いいもの　見せてやるよ。→
I'm gonna take you all on one hell of a ride.
Um, moving on, we have...
[ﾏｲｸ]（生徒）えー
仕切り直して　次は…。
Music Preparation Room
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]（♪♪『エチュード　ホ短調　作品２５－５』）
ぎゃあー！
ださっ。　面白くない。
LAME
Lame.
BORING
Boring.
平均的。　普通。
BORING
Mediocre.
MEDIO
BORING
MEDIOCRE
Pedestrian
Pedestrian.
BORING
MEDIOCRE
Pedestrian
But at least you've got the piece down pat.
でも　課題曲は
完全に入ったみたいね。
完璧に譜面を弾けたって
何も変わらない。
Even playing the sheet music perfectly isn't gonna make a difference.
Chopin's whispering to me.
ショパンが　ささやくんだ。
「ここの　どこに
君がいるんだい？」って。
"Where are you in all this?"
Hey.
ねえ　地区総体の応援　行こうか？
気晴らしがてら。
How about we go cheer them on at Regionals? You could use a change of scenery.
僕はいいよ。
このままじゃ　前のまんま。
I'll pass.
At this rate, it'll only end up like before.
僕は　完璧を超えるんだ。
I'm going to transcend perfection.
《君のように》
Like you.
駄目ー。　応援　行くの。
You're hopeless.
We're gonna go cheer them on.
引きこもってたら
息　詰まっちゃうよ。
You'll suffocate if you shut yourself up in here.
Musicians need to clear their minds every once in a while!
演奏家は
空を見る時間が　必要なの！
SUMIYA
MEIKOU
Last inning!
SUMIYA
MEIKOU
（部員）しっかり　守ってこー！
（部員）三遊間　もっと　絞って！
SUMIYA
MEIKOU
Tighten up the defense!
SUMIYA
MEIKOU
Don't let anything through!
SUMIYA
MEIKOU
You got this!
SUMIYA
MEIKOU
（柏木）頼むよ　椿。
最悪　タイまで　持ちこまないと。
We're counting on you, Tsubaki!
We need to at least tie it up!
分かってる。　あっ…。
I know.
いけー　椿。
Go for it, Tsubaki!
公生。　あっ…。
Kousei...
（主審）プレー！
Play ball!
A famous violinist once said...
《有名なバイオリニストが
言ってたの》
《「音楽は言葉を超える」って》
"Music transcends words."
（主審）ストライク！
（柏木）椿！
Strike!
Tsubaki!
《音を交わすことで
お互いを知り　お互いを理解する》
Through exchanging notes, you get to know one another and learn to understand each other.
（主審）ボール。
（部員）いけ！　三冠王！
Ball!
Let's go, Triple Crown champ!
As if your souls are connected, and your hearts overlapping.
《まるで　魂が結び付き→
Don't miss any meatballs!
心を重ねるように。
それは　楽器を通じての対話》
It's communication through instruments.
《ハーモニーの生み出す奇跡》
Harmony born from a miracle.
（ボールを打つ音）
《その瞬間→
In that moment, music transcends words.
音楽は言葉を超えるのです》
Isn't that awful?
（椿）ひどいと思いません？
女の子に　おんぶさせるなんて。
What kind of boy makes a girl carry him on her shoulders?!
Well, girls are bigger during childhood.
（斉藤）子供のころは
女の子の方が　体が大きいから。
そんな問題じゃないです！
乙女心の問題です。
That's not the point!
It's about a lady's heart.
でも　普段はダメダメなのに
ピアノ弾かせたら　すごくて→
But even though he's hopeless most of the time, he's amazing when he plays the piano.
この前なんて
お客さん総立ちで…。
He even got a standing ovation the other day!
Did I say something funny?
おかしなこと言いました？
いつも同じだ。
Some things never change.
椿は　有馬君の話ばかりする。
You're always going on and on about Arima.
All right! Through the gap!
よっしゃ！　抜けた！
あー！　椿ちゃーん！
Yay, Tsubaki!
（椿）
《やだよ　やだよ　やだよ…》→
No.
No, no...
《分かってる》→
I know I have no right to feel this way.
《こんなこと思う資格なんて
ないってこと》→
《だけど　やっぱり　やだ》→
But I still can't let it go.
《やなもんは　やだ》→
I just can't.
《いつも　一緒。
いつも　そばにいた》→
We were always together. I was always by his side.
《うれしいとき　悲しいときも》→
In times of joy and grief alike.
《でも　いつの間にか
遠くにいる》→
But...
before I knew it, we'd already grown apart.
《私は　そばにいない。
他の誰かがいる》
I'm not by his side.
Someone else is there instead.
（部員）ちょっ　椿！
（柏木）椿？　ストップ　ストップ！
What are you doing?!
Tsubaki!
Stop! Stop!
（椿）《やだよ。
私を見て。　私を見てよ！》→
No...
Look at me!
Look at me, will you?
《そんな目で　誰かを見ないで》
Don't set those eyes on someone else!
（主審）アウト！
Out!
（主審）ゲームセット！
Ballgame!
椿。　私　こっちから帰るわ。
Tsubaki, I'm gonna head this way.
（椿）こっちじゃん　柏木。
But your house is that way, Kashiwagi.
I'm gonna let your boyfriend cheer you up.
彼氏に　なぐさめてもらいなよ。
（椿）はあ？　彼氏？
Boyfriend?
Saitou...
（椿）先輩…。→
公生？
Kousei?
おっす。
Yo.
Yo...
ひい！　ぎゃー！
（椿）公生　恥ずかしい。
Kousei...
This is embarrassing.
At least no one's looking.
誰も見てないよ。
（椿）誰にもバレなかったのに。
何年の付き合いだと思ってんだよ。
But nobody else was onto me.
And how long have we known each other?
（椿）かをちゃんは？
帰ったよ。
Where's Kao?
She went home.
一人で
椿ちゃんのとこに行けって。
She said I should go see you on my own.
After that roll down the hill, you carried me like this even though you were hurt too.
大車輪のときも→
ケガしてるのに
こんなふうに僕を　おぶってさ。
結局　自分も　足を
ハンドボールみたいに腫らしちゃって。
In the end, your ankle swelled up like a balloon.
（椿）そうだっけ？
It did?
子供のころと
ちっとも変わらないんだから。
You haven't changed a bit since we were kids.
変わったよ。
Sure I have.
《心が　よく揺れる》
My heart is always wavering.
無理　無理。　全部　お見通し。
Nice try, but I can read you like a book.
だから　僕には　我慢なんか
しなくていいんだからね。
So you never have to hold back with me, all right?
椿には
心配かけてばかりだったから→
I've always made you worry so much about me,
たまには
僕に心配させてほしいな。
so I wish you'd let me worry about you for a change.
頼りない弟かもしれないけど
僕　頑張るから。
I might be an unreliable kid brother, but I'm gonna do my best.
頑張るから。　だから…。
Since I'm gonna give it my all,
I want you watching me with a smile.
元気な椿に　見ててほしいんだ。
いつまでも
椿に　おんぶに抱っこじゃ→
I can't just let you carry me on your shoulders forever.
カッコ悪いもんね。
それにしても
椿って　見た目より軽いね。
Still, I gotta say...
You're lighter than you look, aren't you?
なっ！
椿は女の子なんだな。
So you are a girl after all!
なっ　何よ　それ！　変なの！
そうだね。　変なこと言った。
Wh-What's that supposed to mean? You're so rude!
Yeah, I guess it was a weird thing to say.
季節が　変わるからかもしれない。
I think the seasons are getting ready to change.
《音楽が何よ　言葉が何よ》
Who cares about music?
Who cares about words?
《私たちには　一緒にいた
長い長い時間があって→
We have all the time that we've spent together.
All those precious memories of all the little things.
ちっぽけで大切な思い出が
たくさんある》
Next time...
（公生）《今度は…。　今度は
僕が　椿を　おぶってあげるね》
Next time, I'll give you a piggyback ride, okay?
負けちゃった。
私のせいで　負けちゃったよ…。
We lost!
We lost and it's all my fault...
ううっ…
みんなで頑張ったのに　悔しいよ。
After we all fought so hard!
I hate this!
悔しいよ…！
《負けて悔しいのに→
Even though I'm upset that I lost...
My ankle's killing me!
落ち込んでるのに→
Even though I'm depressed...
足が痛いのに→
Even though my ankle hurts
How could we lose like that?
and my eyes are stained with tears.
目が涙で
ぐしょぐしょなのに→
最悪なのに→
I don't think I've ever felt worse,
どうして　星が　こんなに
きらきらしてるんだろう》
so why do the stars look so bright tonight?
《髪から　音楽室のにおい》
The scent of the music room in his hair.
《少し荒い　息遣いが聞こえる》
The sound of his slightly ragged breathing.
《涙でぬれた　肩口が温かい》
His shoulder, warm and wet with tears.
《私は　そばにいる》
I am by his side.
《このまま
時間が止まればいいのに》
I wish we could live in this moment forever.
（武士）おはようございます　先生。
Good morning.
（高柳）毎報コンの出場者名簿だ。
付箋のところ　見てみなよ。
This is the list of Maihou contestants.
Check out the flagged name.
（高柳）気合　入るぞ。
You'll be pleasantly surprised.
（武士）ふんっ！
（高柳）ああっ。
（武士）待ってたぜ　２年間。
I've waited two long years for this.
（武士）《積年の屈辱を
晴らすときが　来たぜ！》
It's time to get revenge for all those years of humiliation!
I see you already know.
（落合）もう知ってるようね。
（絵見）何がですか？
About what?
（落合）とぼけたって　駄目よ。
音が躍ってるわ。
You can't fool me.
Not with such spirit in your music.
You're just imagining things.
（絵見）気のせいですよ。
（絵見）《何してるのかと思ったら
やっと出てきた》→
I've been wondering what you were up to,
and now you've finally shown up.
《今度こそ　ギタギタに
ぶちのめしてやるわ！》→
Just you wait. I'm gonna mop the floor with you this time.
Arima Kousei
Sumiya Junior High
Past Accolades
Moriwaki Student Competition - Piano Division
Houllier International Competition
Saiki Competition
1st Place
Winner
Oomori Yuusuke
Hori Preparatory Middle School
《有馬　公生》
Arima Kousei!
Episode 6
The Way Home
I realized I never want to leave your side
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
Episode 7
Whispering Shadows
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
I realized I never want to leave your side
Watch next week too!